



OF THE 



<ORGANIZATION>American Historical Association</ORGANIZATION> 



FOR 



THE YEAR 1908 



IN TWO VOLUMES 

Vol. 11(1) 

Diplomatic Correspondence of the <LOCATION>Republic of Texas</LOCATION> 
: :P»rt:II : . 




GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE 

1911 



1 *) ^ n 7 »! Digitized by CuOOglC 



r 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



EIGHTH REPORT OF THE 
HISTORICAL MANUSCRIPTS COMMISSION. 



DIPLOMATIC CORRESPONDENCE OF THE REPUBLIC OF <LOCATION>TEXAS</LOCATION>. 



PART II. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



DIPLOMATIC CORRESPONDENCE OF THE REPUBLIC OF <LOCATION>TEXAS</LOCATION>. 

EDITED BY 

Profesior of History in the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>. 

PART II. 

CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE <ORGANIZATION>UNITED STATES</ORGANIZATION> (concluded), <LOCATION>MEXICO</LOCATION>, 
AND YUCATAN. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



rN-TEODUOTIOK 

In editing Part II of the Diplomatic Correspondence of the <LOCATION>Republic 
of Texas</LOCATION>, the same difficulties which appeared in deaUng with Part 
I have manifested themselves with much greater intensity, and 
to them have been added some new ones. The effort to restore 
the original grouping has been especially difficult. In the files, 
inclosures have generally been found separate from the letters with 
which they were transmitted and placed in order of dates-; and, in 
the records, though they frequently indicate the arrangement of the 
communications and other matter as sent or received, there is some- 
times such confusion that they become utterly useless for the pur- 
pose. Besides this, some of the letters received, both those sent 
independently and those inclosed with others, have been taken out 
of the "diplomatic" correspondence and filed with other series in 
the archives, such as *' colonization," "financial affairs," "army 
papers," etc.; and the task of discovering them and returning them 
to their places in the correspondence has not been easy. It is hoped, 
however, that, while a httle doubt remains in some cases, the endeavor 
to restore the original arrangement has been fairly successful. 

The principal aim, both in the arrangement of the letters and in 
the annotations, has been to throw as much light as possible on the 
internal relations of the Correspondence. In this way, it is believed, 
will the publication of it be given the highest degree of value for 
the investigator. The external relations, which can be so much 
more easily worked out by readers unable to reach the Texan archives 
but with fair library facilities available, have received much less 
attention. 

Part n has been a little more liberally edited than Part I. Errors 
in the original documents that are evidently the result of pure 
inadvertence have been corrected, with notes where they have 
seemed important enough to call for it, but frequently without. 
The supposition of inadvertence in the case of errors in the use of 
French and Spanish accents has been made wherever there seemed to 
be room for it. But errors in this respect or any other that appear 
to be habitual or due to want of information have, as a general 
rule, been reproduced, or corrected only with annotations. More 
freedom has been used in editing copies that there is reason to sus- 
pect as corrupt than originals and copies that appear to be trust- 
worthy. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



30 INTRODUCTION. 

The classification of the correspondence has been by subject 
matter rather than by the diplomatic office or location of the writer. 
Letters dealing with Spanish relations, for example, are placed 
in the correspondence with <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, even though written by or to the 
Texan charge to <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. 

The system of reference for inclosures, leading from the title 
to the letter with which the inclosure came, and thence sometimes 
to the calendar or another division of the correspondence, may 
now and then try the patience of the reader; but it has been adopted 
as that which will throw the clearest light on the history and the 
relations of each letter. 

Before reaching final conclusions in the study of Part I, the reader 
should compare the corrections and further annotations and the list 
of addenda for Part I given in Part II. 

The diplomatic relations of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> with the European powers 
began in 1837, with the sending of <PERSON>J. Pinckney Henderson</PERSON> on a mis- 
sion to <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. He had letters of credence both 
as agent and as minister plenipotentiary to <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, and pre- 
sumably also to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.** He reached <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in October. The 
efforts to establish relations with <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, 
the <ORGANIZATION>Hanse Towns</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Prussia</LOCATION> were made partly by the ministers in 
<LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and partly by special chargfe. May 20, 
1839, <PERSON>James Hamilton</PERSON> was sent to act as joint agent of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> with 
<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, both in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and on April 18, 1840, he 
was appointed Texan diplomatic commissioner to the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, 
and at the same time received a second commission empowering him 
to treat with both the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. January 20, 1843, 
<PERSON>William H. Daingerfield</PERSON> was commissioned as charg6 d'affaires to 
the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, and the Hanse Towns. While on his mis- 
sion he visited <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> also, and, in fact, undertook some 
correspondence to ascertain through official sources the attitude 
of <LOCATION>Prussia</LOCATION> towards <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. In 1842, <PERSON>Ashbel Smith</PERSON>, then chargfi 
d'affaires to <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, tried to open the way for 
formal negotiations with <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> by a correspondence with General 
<PERSON>Sancho</PERSON>, Spanish minister to <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Washington Irving</PERSON>, 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> minister to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, but nothing came of it; nor did 
<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> nor <PERSON>George W. Terrell</PERSON>, who was commissioned as Texan 
minister to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> in 1846, visit <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> at all. 

Strenuous efforts were made by the Texan government during 
<PERSON>Lamar</PERSON>'s administration to estabUsh amicable relations with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. 
On February 20, 1839, <PERSON>Barnard E. Bee</PERSON> was commissioned both as 
agent and as minister plenipotentiary of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. He went 
toVeraCmz in May; but the Mexican government refused to receive 

a No copies of his letters of credence to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> have been found, but they doubtless had the same fbnn 
as those to <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



INTRODUCTION. 31 

him, and he got no further. On August 9, of the same year, <PERSON>James 
Treat</PERSON> was appointed private and confidential agent of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. He reached <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in December, 183^, and remained until 
November, 1840. On March 20, 1841, <PERSON>James Webb</PERSON> received com- 
missions similar to those which had been given to Bee. He went 
to <PERSON>Vera Cruz</PERSON> in May, but was not allowed to proceed to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. 

On July 20, 1841, President <PERSON>Lamar</PERSON> wrote the governor of Yucat&amp;n, 
which was then in a state of insurrection against the central govern- 
ment of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, inviting him to send an agent to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> with a view 
to the establishment of relations of amity and commerce between the 
two countries. The result was a sort of miUtary convention by 
which the fleet of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> was subsidized to operate against <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> on 
behalf of both <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and Yucat4n, but no treaty was concluded. 

First after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to accord recognition to the RepubUc 
of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> was <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. This was done by a treaty of amity, commerce, 
and navigation concluded September 26, 1839, and ratified February 
14, 1840. A similar treaty between <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> was 
signed November 13, 1840; a convention for British mediation 
between <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, on November 14; and a treaty for the sup- 
pression of the African slave trade, on November 16. For reasons 
which need not be detailed here, the ratifications of these three 
treaties were not exchanged till June 28, 1842. A commercial treaty 
with the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> was signed September 18, 1840, and ratified 
June 15, 1841. A convention of amity, commerce, and navigation 
with the Ilanse Towns was concluded April 17, 1844, and was later 
ratified by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Bremen</LOCATION>; but, doubtless b^ause of the near 
prospect of annexation, it seems never to have been acted on by the 
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. No treaty was concluded with <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. 
In April, 1838, before <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> was formally recognized, an agreement 
was effected with the British Government whereby Texan vessels 
were admitted to the ports of <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> as those of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>; and a 
resolution adopted by the senate of <LOCATION>Bremen</LOCATION> on August 9, 1843, pro- 
vided for the admission of Texan vessels to the ports of <LOCATION>Bremen</LOCATION> on 
the same terms as to port charges and duties as the ships of <LOCATION>Bremen</LOCATION> 
on condition of a reciprocal arrangement by <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 

Of course, until the ratification of the various treaties mentioned, 
the negotiations with the countries with which they were made was 
on a more or less informal basis. Aft^ those with <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> were ratified, charges were sent to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> by both these 
nations; but no other had a diplomatic representative to that repub- 
Uc at any time.** The only charg6 sent by <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> was <PERSON>Charles 
EUiot</PERSON>, whose letter of credence was dated June 28, 1842, and who 

« There is good reason to believe that Mr. 7. <PERSON>T. Crawford</PERSON>, who visited <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> in April, 1837, came as a secret 
agent of <LOCATION>Qieat Britain</LOCATION> to report on its civil and political condition. Count de Saligny undertook a similar 
mission for <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> early in 1839, and Capt. <PERSON>Victor Pirson</PERSON> came openly as the agent of <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> in 1842. 
None of these, however, appears to have had any dlplomatlo authority. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



32 nwpRODUonoN. 

reached <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> in August, and remained till the eve of annexation. 
The first charge of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was Count <PERSON>A. de Saligny</PERSON>,** who was accred- 
ited October 2, 1839, and reached <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> m February, 1840. He 
left <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> in March, 1841, but returned for a brief period in 1842. 
Towards the end of that year, he was succeeded by "<PERSON>Viscount J. de 
Cramayel</PERSON>. Some two years later, <PERSON>Cramayel</PERSON> left <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Saligny</PERSON> 
returned. This time he continued in the capacity of charg6 until the 
mission was ended by annexation. 

The letters printed in Part II have been taken mainly from the 
file of originals received and copies kept of letters sent from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 
and from the transcripts in the books of the <ORGANIZATION>Department of State</ORGANIZATION>. 
Book 55, from which some of them were obtained, is evidently the 
original kept by <LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> for his missions to the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, and the Hanse Towns. It is, however, the only book from 
any of the Eiuropean legations that has been found in the Texan 
archives. That it was brought to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and delivered to the Secre- 
tary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION> is shown by the letter of <LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>, February 
2, 1846; and its contents place its identity beyond question. 

Just as this part was ready, as the editor thought, to send to press, 
a considerable mass of the correspondence was found in books which 
had not been suspected of containing it. The reasons why it had 
escaped discovery are that the mass of matter in the books is so great 
and the indexes so imperfect. The indexes are, in fact — ^where they 
exist at all — often worse than useless, in that they are misleading. 
Many of the letters in the newly discovered group belong to the 
period of Correspondence with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> covered by Part I. 
They make it possible, in some cases and to a certain extent, to fdi- 
low both sides of the correspondence where the letters already pub- 
lished had given but one. While the editor does not feel absolutely 
certain that some letters may not still <PERSON>Kave</PERSON> evaded his search, 
he hopes that little of importance preserved in the Texan archives 
and properly to be included in the correspondence now remains 
impublished. 

The editor is under special obligations to State Librarian <PERSON>E. W. 
Winkler</PERSON>, who several years ago gave the Correspondence here printed 
its first approach toward rational and useful arrangement, and con- 
sequent availability for the student. Mr. <PERSON>Winkler</PERSON>'s minute knowl- 
edge of the Texan archives and of southwestern history in general 
have made his freely rendered assistance of the highest value. Grate- 
ful acknowledgment is made also to instructors <PERSON>Walton H. Hamilton</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>J. L. Worley</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, for help in verifying 
and arranging the copies; to Profs. <PERSON>Lilia M. Casls</PERSON> and <PERSON>E. J. Villavaso</PERSON>, 
also of this university, for verifying, respectively, the Spanish and 

o Thus written by himself. The name is usually given in official documents fmanating trom the Freocli 
Government as "Dubois de Saligny." 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



INTRODUCTION. 33 

French letters; and to Mr. <PERSON>C. T. Neu</PERSON>, fellow in history in the same 
institution for 1908-09, and now teacher of history in the high school 
at <LOCATION>Greenville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, for help in various details, and especially in the 
preparation of the Calendars. 

<PERSON>George P. Garrison</PERSON>, 

<PERSON>Unwersity</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 



Note. 



<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>D. C</PERSON>, December 24, 1910. 

The <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> suffered a severe loss in the death of Professor 
<PERSON>George P. Garrison</PERSON> during the progress of this work. Professor 
<PERSON>Garrison</PERSON> died in July, 1910, before reading a single page of the proof 
of this second part of the "Diplomatic Correspondence of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>." 
The labor of proof-reading, therefore, fell upon others, who did not 
possess the special knowledge, experience, and full equipment enjoyed 
by him. This has occasioned some delay, and may have resulted in 
some inaccuracy. 

Professor <PERSON>Garrison</PERSON> had for years been preparing the material for 
these volumes, and, fortunately, left it in very good shape for pub- 
lication. So far as the collation of the text is concerned, he gave 
assurances of completeness and accuracy. The list of material 
already published was prepared by him, and he left, to be used with 
the documents as they were published, notes explaining and illus- 
trating the subject. These have been inserted in the places desig- 
nated by him. The volume practically stands as his labor. 

The proof-reading has been done by Miss <PERSON>Catharine Bowes</PERSON>, Miss 
<PERSON>Georgia Sanderlin</PERSON>, and Miss <PERSON>Bertha M. Emerson</PERSON>. The <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> 
acknowledges the courteous assistance of Professor <PERSON>Eugene C. Barker</PERSON>^ 
of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>. 

39728'— VOL 2, pt 1—11 3 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



TEXAN DIPLOMATIC CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE <ORGANIZATION>UNITED STATES</ORGANIZATION>, 1843 
TO 1846 (WITH ADDITIONAL LETTERS, 1835-1842), WITH <LOCATION>MEXICO</LOCATION> AND 
YUCATAN, AND WITH GREAT <LOCATION>BRITAIN</LOCATION> AND THE EUROPEAN STATES. 



CALENDAR OF CORRESPONDENCE HITHERTO 

ADDENDA TO CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE UNITB|&gt; STATES, 1835 TO 1846.« 

<ORGANIZATION>Burnley</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>; Gc\iii^\l, 18$3 i| extract).: . F&amp;U)ire*ta secure loan in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Meoldrahda'and Official Correspondence, 143. 

<PERSON>Williams</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, March 11, 1839 (extract). Negotiations for a loan in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 145-146. 

<PERSON>Reily</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 10, 1844 (extract) . Fears that annexation will be delayed 
several years. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 396-397. 

DonelBon to <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>, December 10, 1844. Measures adopted by <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to 
guard interests of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> in case of renewal of war by <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> because of annexation. 
<ORGANIZATION>Senate Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 9th Tex. Cong., 191-195. 

<PERSON>Allen</PERSON> to DonelBon, December 13, 1844. Attitude of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> toward delay of annexa- 
tion and opposition of <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to Mexican method of prosectlting war against 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Senate Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 9th Tex. Cong., 195-197. 

<PERSON>Kaufman</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, September 30, 1845 (extract). Discusses his position as Texan 
chaig6 to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 495- 
496. 

<PERSON>Kaufman</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 3, 1845 (extract). Announces his return to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 503-504. 

CORRESPONDENCE WPTH <LOCATION>MEXICO</LOCATION>. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Filisola</LOCATION>, April 22, 1836 [No. 1]. Announces his defeat and capture, 
and gives orders for the withdrawal of <LOCATION>Filisola</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Gaona</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Bexar</LOCATION>, and of <PERSON>Urrea</PERSON> to 
<LOCATION>Guadalupe Victoria</LOCATION>. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>), August 23 and Sep- 
tember 6, 1836; <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' R^ter, L, 337. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Filisola</LOCATION>, April 22, 1836 [No. 2]. Directs that no damage be done prop- 
erty of citizens of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, September 6, 1836. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Filisola</LOCATION>, April 22, 1836 [No. 3]. Orders that prisoners taken at 
C6pano be sent to <LOCATION>San FeHpe</LOCATION>. Tel^raph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, September 6, 1836. 

Filisola to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, April 28, 1836. Cessation of hostilities in obedience to <LOCATION>Santa 
Anna</LOCATION>'s orders concerning the armistice. Property will be respected. Deplores past 
plundering. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, L, 337. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Filisola</LOCATION>, May 14, 1836 (extract). Orders that the treaty of May 14, 
1836, between <LOCATION>Burnet</LOCATION> and himself be complied with. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, L, 413; <ORGANIZATION>Tele</ORGANIZATION>- 
graph and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> R^:i8ter, August 23, 1836. 

Filisola to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, May 25, 1836. Promises obedience to terms of agreement 
between <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Roister</ORGANIZATION>, August 23, 1836. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Burnet</ORGANIZATION>, June 9, 1836. Protests against violation of Treaty of May 14, 
1836, with respect to his own treatment, to that of <PERSON>Woll</PERSON>, and to the failure to exchange 

a See the calendar of correspondenoe with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 1835-1845, hitherto printed, in Part I, 
paflet 25-40. 

35 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



n/ 



36 <ORGANIZATION>AMEBIOAN HISTOBICAIi ASSOCIATION</ORGANIZATION>. 

priflonen. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, LI, 191; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, October 4, 1836, 
and March 23, 1842; <ORGANIZATION>Austin City Gazette</ORGANIZATION>, March 30, 1842. 

Burnet to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, June 10, 1836. Answers protest of <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON> in his letter of 
June 9, 1836. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, LI, 191; <ORGANIZATION>Telegraph tod Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, October 4, 
1836. 

<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, September 4, 1836. <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> believes that nations 
have the right to change their governments as the people may dictate, and refuses to 
interpose in affairs of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> over the protest of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, 
LI, 336. 

<PERSON>Lamar</PERSON> to Citizens of <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> F^, Aptsl U, }8^. Announces entry of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> among 
the ^unily of nations as a free Republic, mvitSi p^ple df <LOCATION>Santa F6</LOCATION> to share blessings of 
liberty, and promises to send Commissioners to cement union between <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> F6. ; <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> JoumsJ, <LOCATION>Sth Tex</LOCATION>. O^yog., Appendix. X48^150| <ORGANIZATION>Journal of Consulta</ORGANIZATION>- 
tion, Addrebs of <PERSON>Lamar</PERSON> to Ciii*wis of <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION>* ?^. 12-r4..* ;.•*'. 

<PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON> to <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Burnley</ORGANIZATION>, July 7, 1840. * Discusses relations between 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and between <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and Yucatan. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong. , 
Appendix, 281-284. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, November 5, 1836. Uiges importance of <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON> going 
in person to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to secure the mediation of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in settlement of 
boundary question between <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, <ORGANIZATION>LXII</ORGANIZATION>, 115; The 
Red-Lander (<LOCATION>San Augustine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>), April 14, 1842 (extract). 

<PERSON>Wright</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lamar</PERSON>, March 18, 1841 (extract). Makes chaige against <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> for 
acceptance of a bribe for the release of <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>. The Red-Lander, September 29, 
1842. 

<ORGANIZATION>Arista</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Lamar</PERSON>, April 21, 1841. States that the expedition which is to set out from 
the <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION> is for the purpose of punishing the Indians, and not intended to attack 
the Texans. Quarterly of the <ORGANIZATION>Texas State Historical Association</ORGANIZATION>, VII, 173-174. 

<PERSON>Lamar</PERSON> to Inhabitants of <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> F^, and other portions of <LOCATION>Mexico East</LOCATION> of the <LOCATION>Rio 
Grande River</LOCATION>, June 5, 1841. Calls attention to his letter of April 14, 1840, repeats 
invitation then given, explains advantages of a union between <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> F6 
region, and announces appointment of commissioners to e£fect this union. Journal of 
Consultation, Address of <PERSON>Lamar</PERSON> to <ORGANIZATION>Citizens of Santa</ORGANIZATION> F6, 3-12. 

Bee to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, December 27, 1841. Does not believe that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> can be con- 
quered by <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, as the people of the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> will give <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> aid, and hopes that 
<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> will treat well the prisoners taken in the <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> F6 expedition. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in 
1842, p. 215; <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, LXII, 49; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, March 23, 
1842. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, January 13, 1842. <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> is commissioned by <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to 
treat with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> for the recognition of Texan independence. Proposes peace on 
condition of an indemnity of $5,000,000 to be paid by <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in 
1842, p. 220; <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, <ORGANIZATION>LXII</ORGANIZATION>, 50; Telegraph and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> R^ter, March 23, 
1842; <ORGANIZATION>Austin City Gazette</ORGANIZATION>, March 30, 1842. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to Bee, February 6, 1842. Thanks Bee for past favors. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> must 
keep <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. A freak of fortune alone has given <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> a victory. The prisoners taken 
will be treated according to generally recognized principles. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in 1842, p. 216; 
<PERSON>Nilee</PERSON>' Register, <ORGANIZATION>LXII</ORGANIZATION>, 50; Tel^raph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, March 23, 1842. 

<LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, February 18, 1842. <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON>, as a citizen of the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>, has no right to treat in behalf of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> has won many victories in the 
past over <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and has suffered a single defeat. Five million dollars too small an 
indemnity. Texan brutalities. Expresses personal gratitude to <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. To 
acknowledge Texan independence would be to sacrifice <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s noble stand on 
slavery. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in 1842, p. 221; <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, <ORGANIZATION>LXII</ORGANIZATION>, 50; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas 
Register</ORGANIZATION>, March 23, 1842; <ORGANIZATION>Austin City Gazette</ORGANIZATION>, March 30, 1842. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



CAIiBNDAB OF PBINTED OOBBESPOKDBKOE. <ORGANIZATION>S7 

Hamilton to Santa Anna</ORGANIZATION>, March 21, 1842. <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON> abhors people to whom he 
owes his life. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s violation of her agreement with colonists was one cause of the 
revolution. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s only victory was the <LOCATION>Alamo</LOCATION>. Defies <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON>. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in 
1842, p. 227; <LOCATION>Tdegraph</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> R^ter, April 13, 1842. 

<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>, March 21, 1842 (extract). Defends the Texan conduct of 
the revolution, particularly the treatment of <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION>. Justifies the <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> 
F6 expedition. States future attitude of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> toward <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, 
LXII, 98. 

S&lt;»nervell to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, March 25, 1842. Somervell has taken chaige of troops, and 
reports dissatis^tion among them. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 
172-173. 

<LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 1, 1842. Texan blockade of Mexican ports. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 201. 

<LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 15, 1842. <LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> 's efforts to co-operate with <PERSON>H. 
Washington</PERSON> in preparation for a descent upon Mexican coast. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and 
Official Correspondence, 201-203. 

<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Somervell</LOCATION>, October 3, 1842. Orders concentration of such troops as are 
willing to invade <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> upon the southwestern boundary, and invasion of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in 
case prospects for success ofiter. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 7th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 3-4. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Somervell</LOCATION>, October 13, 1842. Orders Somervell to proceed to south- 
western frontier, to organize troops, to move with secrecy, and to invade <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> if 
success seem probable. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 7th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 5-6. 

Somervell to <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON>, November 7, 1842. Reports progress in oiganization of 
troops. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 7th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 10-11. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Somervell</LOCATION>, November 9, 1842. Gives method of securing supplies for 
troops. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 7th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 6. 

Somervell to <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, November 14, 1842. Reports progress in oiganizing troops 
and gives information as to location of Mexican troops on border and disposition of 
Texan prisoners. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 7th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 11-12. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Somervell</LOCATION>, November 19, 1842. Regrots poor oiganization and disci- 
pline of the troops, repeats orders to enlist none but those willing to invade <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, and 
urges energetic action. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 7th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 7-9. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hamilton to Somervell</ORGANIZATION>, November 21, 1842. Urges prompt but cautious advance in 
order to avoid surprise, and directs disposition of supplies in case troops are disbanded. 
<ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 7th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 9-10. 

Somervell to <PERSON>Hill</PERSON>, February 1, 1843. Gives detailed account of his invasion of 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 9th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 70-75; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas 
Register</ORGANIZATION>, February 22, 1843. 

<PERSON>Hill</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Hockley</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>, September 26, 1843. Instructions for arrangement 
of armistice with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> through the mediation of <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>. The Red-Lander, 
June 1, 1844. 

0ORRS8PONDBN0B WITH YUCATIn. 

<LOCATION>Mooro</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Cooke</PERSON>, August 28, 1840. Reports his movements from July 2^August 28, 
1840. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 232-237. 

<PERSON>Peraza</PERSON> to <PERSON>Roberts</PERSON>, September 16, 1841. <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> is preparing to invade Yucat&amp;n 
by land and by sea. Asks that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> send two or three of her vessels to aid in repelling 
the Mexican squadron. Offers pecuniary inducements. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 15-17. 

<PERSON>Roberts</PERSON> to <PERSON>Peraza</PERSON>, September 17, 1841. <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will aid <LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION>. Accepts <PERSON>Peraza</PERSON>'s 
proposals with some modifications. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 17-19. 

<PERSON>Peraza</PERSON> to <PERSON>Roberts</PERSON>, September 17, 1841. The proposals as modified by <PERSON>Roberts</PERSON> are 
accepted. Adds one article and asks that it be accepted. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 19-20. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



88 AMEBICAN HISTOBICAL A8S0GIATI0K. 

<PERSON>Archer</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, September 18, 1841. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> is to keep three veseels in reftdineas 
for <PERSON>Bea</PERSON>. The Govemment of YucatAn will fumiah him with $8,000 each month. Secret 
orders indeed. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 12-13. 

<PERSON>Archer</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, September 18, 1841 . Secret orders. He is to sail for Sisal, capture 
the enemy's vessels if possible, and co-operate with the forces of <LOCATION>Yucatin</LOCATION> generally. 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 13-15. 

<PERSON>Roberts</PERSON> to P^aza, September 18, 1841. A number of Texan vessels have been 
ordered to proceed to Sisal. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 20-21. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lemus</PERSON>, January 8, 1842. Is at Sisal with one ship and two schooners ready 
to carry out the treaty on the part of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 25. 

<PERSON>Lemus</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, January 8, 1842. The governor will receive him on Monday. 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 25. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to Rej6n, January 10, 1842. Is surprised that <ORGANIZATION>Yucat&amp;n</ORGANIZATION> has entered into a 
treaty with the Central Govemment of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> . <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>. To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 26-27 . 

Rej6n to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, January 12, 1842. The treaty with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> should surprise no one. 
Yucat&amp;n has not renounced her right to be incorporated in the <LOCATION>Mexican Union</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, 
To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 27-29. 

<PERSON>Gray</PERSON> to the Mexican and Yucatin commissionerB, January 12, 1842. Fearing for 
the safety of <PERSON>Commodore Moore</PERSON> he will detain them as hostages. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People 
of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 31. 

<PERSON>Gray</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, January 12, 1842. Has deemed it advisable to detain the commis- 
sioners of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and Yucat&amp;n as hostages. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 30. 

Rej6n to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, January 12, 1842. The commander of the Texan vessel Atistm took 
the Mexican and Yucatan commissioners prisoners. Demands that they be set at 
liberty. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 32. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to Rej6n, January 14, 1842. Has never doubted the right of <LOCATION>Yucatin</LOCATION> to dis- 
pose of her political and natural rights as she may deem proper. Leaves for Sisal 
to-day. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 29-30. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to Rej6n, January 15, 1842. Regrets that the Mexican and Yucatan commis- 
sioners were detained; has ordered that they be set at liberty. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People 
of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 32-33. 

Rej6n to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, January 18, 1842. Incloses a copy of a decree of the <ORGANIZATION>Congress of 
Yucat&amp;n</ORGANIZATION>, October 25, 1841, relative to <PERSON>Peraza</PERSON>'s instructions; copy of agreement made 
by <ORGANIZATION>Yucat&amp;n</ORGANIZATION> with <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, September 18, 1841; and copy of convention with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, 
December 28, 1841, for the reimion of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 33-34. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to Rej6n, January 31, 1842. Has received his letter of January 18, 1842; 
<ORGANIZATION>Yucat&amp;n</ORGANIZATION> should have a flag so that her vessels would not be molested by the Texan 
warships. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 35. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lemus</PERSON>, February 25, 1842. Requests that $8,000 be placed in his hands as 
per the agreement. Has been cruising near <PERSON>Vera Cruz</PERSON>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 37. 

<PERSON>Lemus</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, February 26, 1842. An order has been issued for the payment of 
the $8,000. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 38. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Cdrdenas</LOCATION>, March 7, 1842. The rumor that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will make war on <LOCATION>Yucat</LOCATION>^ 
vessels is unfoimded. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 38-39. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to Celerayan, March 7, 1842. The rumor that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will make war on 
<LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION> vessels is unfounded. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 39-40. 

Cirdenas to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, March 7, 1842. The rumor that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> would make war on 
<LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION> vessels was not credited by the Govemment of Yucatan. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the Peo- 
ple of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 40-41. 

Celerayan to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, March 7, 1842. No credit has been given to the rumor that 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s acts were to be hostile to YucatAn. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 41. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



CALENDAR OP PRINTED CORRESPONDENCE. 39 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Lemue</LOCATION>, March 8, 1842. Arrived at <LOCATION>Campeche</LOCATION> on March 6. The rumors 
that his acts were to be hostile to <LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION> were spread to in j ure his reputation . <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, 
To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 41-42. 

<PERSON>Lemus</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, March 18, 1842. The governor is gratified at the contents of 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s letter of March 8. The rumor was never credited. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 43. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lemus</PERSON>, March 28, 1842. Will cruise a few days before Vera Cruz ; received 
$6,000 from the collector at <LOCATION>Carmen</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 52-53. 

<PERSON>Lemus</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, March 29, 1842. Serves notice that the Government of <LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION> 
is willing for <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to withdraw with the squadron under his command. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, 
To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 53-54. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lemus</PERSON>, April 19, 1842. Regrets the determination of the Government of 
<LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION> as expressed in the matter of the withdrawal of the squadron. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To 
the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 54-55. 

<PERSON>Lemus</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, April 22, 1842. The accounts have been adjusted with Mr. <PERSON>Seeger</PERSON>. 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 55. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lemus</PERSON>, April 24, 1842. Sails for <LOCATION>Campeche</LOCATION> in an hour. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the 
<ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 56. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to, <LOCATION>Cdrdenas</LOCATION>, April 25 [?], 1842. Will give the necessary orders for the safety 
of the vessels mentioned in his letter of April [26]?. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 58. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lemus</PERSON>, April 26, 1842. Regrets that the monthly payments will be sus- 
pended. <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> has proven her friendship to <LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 59. 

<PERSON>Cardenas</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, April 26, 1842* The flag of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> is still the flag of <LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION>. 
Names several schooners that fly this flag and hopes they will not be molested . <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, 
To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 56-58. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lemus</PERSON>, May 26, 1842. Captain <PERSON>Seeger</PERSON> will visit M^rida to settle for the 
money still due <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 76. 

<PERSON>De Lleigo</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, June 8, 1842. Incloses a copy of the official conmiunication 
addressed to Mr. <PERSON>Seeger</PERSON>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 76-77. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to C&amp;rdenas, January 16, 1843. Incloses a letter for the governor. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, 
To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 121. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to the governor of <LOCATION>Yucatdn</LOCATION>, January 17, 1843. Asks for $8,000 so that he 
can refit and attack the conmion enemy. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 119-121. 

<LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, January 31, 1843. Mr. <PERSON>Peraza</PERSON> is fully authorized on the 
subject of <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s letter of January 16. The pecuniary aid will be given as soon as 
<PERSON>Peraza</PERSON> arrives in <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 122. 

<PERSON>Mendez</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, February 3, 1843. <PERSON>Peraza</PERSON> has already sailed with the $8,000. 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 122-124. 

Cdrdenas to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, February 5, 1843. Has complied with <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s request of Janu- 
ary 16, and placed the letter in the hands of the governor. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 124. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Mendez</PERSON>, February 23, 1843. Received his commimication of January 27, 
1843. Had concluded an agreement with <PERSON>Peraza</PERSON> a few days before. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the 
<ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 12&amp;-129. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION>, February 24, 1843. Has concluded an agreement with 
<PERSON>Peraza</PERSON>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 129. 

<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Moigan</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON>, March 23, 1843. Authorizes Morgan and <PERSON>Bryan</PERSON> to 
secure possession of national vessels, equipments, etc., to call upon the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 
in case of resistance, and to deprive <PERSON>E. W. Moore</PERSON> of the command which he has held 
contrary to orders since October 29, 1842. The Morning Star, June 13, 1843. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION>, April 28, 1843. Informs him of his arrival at Sisal. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, 
To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 148. 



Digitized by VjOOQIC 



40 <ORGANIZATION>AMEBICAN HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION</ORGANIZATION>. 

<LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, May 1, 1843. Glad <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> has arrived. The Yucatdn Gov- 
ernment has ordered a renewal of hostilities with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 148. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION>, May 15, 1843. Thinks he should have been consulted in 
the making of the treaty of capitulation, since it stipulates that he is not to attack 
transport vessels. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 157-158. 

<LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, May 20, 1843. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s objection to the treaty is well founded 
but it was entered into to free <PERSON>Yucatin</PERSON> of the capitulating forces. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the 
<ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 158-159. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Meddez</LOCATION>, May 22, 1843. Asks for the services of a vessel. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the 
<ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 163. 

<PERSON>Mendez</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, May 22, 1843. The schooner Independencia will be placed under 
his orders. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 167. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <PERSON>Mendez</PERSON>, May 26, 1843. Would like to use the Independencia for another 
cruise. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 163-164. 

<PERSON>Mendez</PERSON> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, May 26, 1843. Has no objection to his using the Independencia. 
<PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 164. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jime</PERSON> 1, 1843. Requests him to remit the balance of the 
18,000 that was due on May 30. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 166. 

<LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, June 24, 1843. The Government of <LOCATION>Yucatin</LOCATION> will pay the 
rest of the $8,000, but thereafter can pay no more. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 
167-168. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION>, June 27, 1843. Has drawn on him for $300. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the 
<ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 176. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION>, June 28, 1843. Leaves for Sisal to get the $2,000 that is still 
due him. Should Yucatdn be again involved in war it will be a pleasure to come to 
her aid again. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 177. 

<PERSON>Moore</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barbachano</LOCATION>, June 30, 1843. In consequence of President <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>'s proc- 
lamation, is anxious to get back to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Asks for an order for $2,000. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To 
the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 177. 

Barbachano to <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, July 6, 1843. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s brother has received $1,700 which 
with the $300 previously received clears the debt. <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>, To the <ORGANIZATION>People of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, 178. 

CORRESPONDENCE WITH GREAT <LOCATION>BRITAIN</LOCATION>. 

<PERSON>Irion</PERSON> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, August 3, 1837 (extract). Captain <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> of the Invincible 
transcended his orders in capturing the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> is to make a candid 
statement to the English Government and express the regrets of the Texan Govern- 
ment. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4tli Tex. Cong., 6-6 A 

Certificate of <PERSON>Carpizo</PERSON>, August 11, 1837 . The affair of the <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION> and the capture 
of the <PERSON>Eliza RusseU</PERSON>, Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 
16-17; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, November 5, 1837. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, October [26], 1837. Apologizes for the seizure and deten- 
tion of the <PERSON>Eliza RusseU</PERSON>. Report House Committee on. Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. 
Cong., 13; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, November 5, 1837. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, October 31, 1837. Has received <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>'s of the 26th. 
Report House Conmiittee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 14; copy inclosed 
with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, November 5, 1837. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, November 5, 1837 (extract). Incloses copies of correspondence 
with <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> concerning the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claims. Report House Committee on 
Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 13-14. 

a This report contains, besides the letters caloidared, considerable matter not belonging to the Diplo- 
matic Correspondence, but nevertheless pertinent to the British clahns. Only one copy of it, so far as I 
have been able to learn, is in existence, and that belongs to Mr. <PERSON>Richard Borgess</PERSON> of £1 Paso, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, who has 
kindly Irat it to the editor to use in preparing this yolome. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



CALENDAE OF PRINTED CORRESPONDENCE. 41 

Protest of <PERSON>Joeeph Ruasell</PERSON> and others, December 2, 1837 (extract). The capture and * 
detention of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON>. Statement of the claim and description of various 
docimients submitted to sustain it. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 
4th Tex. Cong., 20-23; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Tolme</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, December 20, 1837. 

<PERSON>Tolme</PERSON> a to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, December 20, 1837. Transmits extracts from the protest 
of <PERSON>Joseph Russell</PERSON> relative to the capture of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON>. Report House Com- 
mittee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 20-23. 

<ORGANIZATION>Lizardi &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, January 5, 1838. Gives an account of the seizure of 
goods carried by the <ORGANIZATION>Little Penn</ORGANIZATION>. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th 
Tex. Cong., 15-16; copy inclosed with <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, January 24, 1838. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, January 24, 1838 (extract). Transmits copy of a letter 
from <ORGANIZATION>Lizardi &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> with statement of property seized on the <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION>. British 
Government can not doubt, since <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>'s letter of October 26, that the Texan 
authorities will order immediate restitution. Report House Committee on Foreign 
Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 14; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, January 30, 
1838. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, January 25, 1838. Has received <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>'s of January 
24; but, being without instructions on the subject, can only transmit them to his 
Govenmient. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 18; 
copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, January 30, 1838. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, January 30, 1838. Incloses correspondence with <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> 
as to damages in the case of the <ORGANIZATION>Little Penn</ORGANIZATION>. Does not regard the claim as just, but 
suggests necessity for prompt attention to it. Report House Committee on Foreign 
Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 14-18. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, February 19, 1838. Transmits documents relative to the 
case of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON>. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. 
Cong., 19; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Irioja</LOCATION>, March 8, 1838. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, February 20, 1838. Acknowledges receipt of <LOCATION>Palmer- 
ston</LOCATION>'s of the 19th with accompanying documents; will transmit them to his Govern- 
ment for advice. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 23; 
copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, March 8, 1838. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, March 8, 1838. Transmits <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> of February 
19, 1838, with inclosmres. Seizure of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> legal. Admissions obtained 
from <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 
19-26. 

<PERSON>Irion</PERSON> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, May 20, 1838 (extract). The Texan Government has never 
authorized nor sanctioned violations of neutrality by its officers. The evidence of 
illegal seizure in the case of the <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION> is not satisfactory. The appointment 
of an English agent in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> would greatly facilitate the adjustment of private claims. 
Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 6-7. 

<PERSON>Irion</PERSON> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, June 6, 1838 (extract). <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> has made no appropriation to 
pay the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claim. Texan Government not disposed to reject just claims, 
but it will be difficult to adjust them without a resident English agent. Report 
House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 7. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, August 24, 1838. Refers to correspondence concerning 
the <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claims and asks what has been done to fulfill the 
promises made. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 27; 
copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, September 5, 1838. 

Statement of Captain <PERSON>Russell</PERSON>'s claim, September [1], 1838. Report House Com- 
mittee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 44; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Swain</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stevens 
A Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Arrangoiz</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten &lt;fc Co.</ORGANIZATION>,&amp; December 12, 1838. 

• Imx»x)peiiy given as "Tolene" In the printed copy. ^ Printed as "Arranquiz, Drooster, &amp; Co." 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



42 <ORGANIZATION>AMEBICAN HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION</ORGANIZATION>. 

<PERSON>Hend</PERSON>^^on to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, September 3, 1838. Acknowledges receipt of <LOCATION>Palmer- 
ston</LOCATION>'s communication of August 24. Defends the condemnation of the Abispa and 
denies that the <PERSON>Brutus</PERSON> took any goods from the <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION>. The President recom- 
mended to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> an appropriation to pay the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claims, and it failed 
only because the owner failed to appear personally, or by his authorized agent, to fix 
the simi justly due. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 
28-30; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, September 5, 1838. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to Inon, September 5, 1838. Recites correspondence with <PERSON>Irion</PERSON> relative 
to the <ORGANIZATION>Little Penn</ORGANIZATION> claims and sends copies of correspondence with <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> on that 
subject. Complains of the unsatisfactory nature of the evidence furnished him by the 
Texan Government. Less difficulty in dealing with the case of the <PERSON>Elua Russell</PERSON>. 
Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 26-31. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Irion</PERSON>, October 28, 1838 (extract). Prays to be furnished immediately 
with more definite information concerning the British claims. Report House Com- 
mittee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 32. 

<PERSON>Backhouse</PERSON> to [<ORGANIZATION>Swain, Stevens &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>], November 1, 1838. Summarizes the histcury 
of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claim. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. 
Cong., 42; copy inclosed with <ORGANIZATION>Swain, Stevens &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Arrangoiz</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, 
December 12, 1838. 

<PERSON>Adam</PERSON> to [<PERSON>Nash</PERSON>], November 20, 1838. Has seen Mr. <PERSON>Backhouse</PERSON> relative to the <PERSON>Elua 
Russell</PERSON> claims and will communicate whatever he may say. Report House Committee 
on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 42; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Swain</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stevens A Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
to <LOCATION>Arrangoiz</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, December 12, 1838. 

<PERSON>Adam</PERSON> to [<PERSON>Nash</PERSON>], November 21, 1838. Mr. <PERSON>Backhouse</PERSON> states that the case of the 
<PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> is still before the Queen's advocate. Report House Committee on 
Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 43; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Swain</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stevens A Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
to <LOCATION>Arrangoiz</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten A Co.</ORGANIZATION>, December 12, 1838. 

<PERSON>Adam</PERSON> to <PERSON>Nash</PERSON>, November 25, 1838. Has conmiunicated the letter received yes- 
terday to Mr. <PERSON>Backhouse</PERSON>, who replied that he hoped soon to be able to give informar- 
tion in regard to the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON>. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 
4th Tex. Cong., 43; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Swain</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stevens A Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Arrangoiz</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten A 
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, December 12, 1838. 

<PERSON>Irion</PERSON> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, November 28, 1838 (extract). <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>'s course as to the 
British claims for indemnity approved. He is authorized to settle the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> 
claims for any amount up to the £865 demanded. The Texan Government is con- 
vinced the Mexicans got most of the goods from the <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION>. The Government 
is not disposed to evade any just claims for indemnity. Report House Committee 
on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 8-10. 

<PERSON>Backhouse</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Swain</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Stevens A Co.</ORGANIZATION>, December [1], 1838. In reply to theirs of 
November 28, sends a letter from <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to Shields, British consul at <LOCATION>Laguna</LOCATION>, 
directing him to assist Captain <PERSON>Russell</PERSON> in the case against him at that place. Report 
House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 43; copy inclosed with 
<PERSON>Swain</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stevens A Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Arrangoiz</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten A Co.</ORGANIZATION>, December 12, 1838. 

<PERSON>Swain</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Stevens &lt;fe Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Arrangoiz</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten A Co.</ORGANIZATION>, December 12, 1838. Asks 
<PERSON>Arrangoiz</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Droosten A Co.</ORGANIZATION> to write to agents of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claims at <LOCATION>New 
Orleans</LOCATION> directing them to urge the settlement of the claims. Report House Com- 
mittee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 41-44; copy inclosed with <ORGANIZATION>Vogelgsang A 
Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Webb</PERSON>, April 16, 1839. 

again to the <ORGANIZATION>British Claims</ORGANIZATION>. Report Hoiise Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th 
Tex. Cong., 33. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to Bee, March 10, 1839 (extract). Hopes to be able to settle the claims 
with the British Government soon. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 
4th Tex. Cong., 32. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



CALBNDAB OF PBIKTED CORRESPONDENCE. 43 

Irion to <LOCATION>Henderson</LOCATION>, March 20, 1839 (extract). A claim for indemnity in the case 
of the <PERSON>Elisa Russell</PERSON> has been made on the Texan Government. Its justice has been 
acknowledged by the president, who has promised to recommend payment. Report 
House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 6. 

<ORGANIZATION>YogelgBango &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Webb</PERSON>, April 16, 1839. Have had no answer to requests 
made for the settlement of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claims through <PERSON>Thomas Toby</PERSON> and others. 
Inclose correepondence concerning the claims. Report House Committee on Foreign 
Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 40-44. 

<PERSON>Crawford</PERSON> to <PERSON>Webb</PERSON>, April 17, 1839. Asks on behalf of <ORGANIZATION>G. Vogelgsang &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, agents 
for the owner of the <PERSON>Eliza RusseU</PERSON>, attention to his claims. Report House Committee 
on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 40-44. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION>, April 24, 1839. Appreciates his interest in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>; thinks he can 
do much in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> to secure the recognition of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Incloses a 
memorandum of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and OflEicial Correspondence, 148-151. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 10, 1839 (extract). Incloses a letter from <ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> to Pal- 
merston on behalf of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will soon be accorded recognition. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Mem- 
oranda and OflEicial Correspondence, 151. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, June 10, 1839. <PERSON>Incloses Jones</PERSON>'s Memorandum on <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Oflicial Correspondence, 151-152; copy inclosed in <LOCATION>Hughes</LOCATION> to 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 10, 1839. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION>, June 10, 1839. Thanks him&gt;for his letter on <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>; the sub- 
ject is important but diflScult. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and OflEicial Correspondence, 152; 
copy inclosed with <ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 10, 1839. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jime</PERSON> 10, 1839, midnight. <LOCATION>Incloses Palmerston</LOCATION>'s letter of June 10, 
1839. Believes <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will soon be recognized by <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and 
Ofl&amp;cial Correspondence, 152-153. 

Burnet to <PERSON>Crawford</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jime</PERSON> 14, 1839. Acknowledges receipt of <PERSON>Crawford</PERSON>'s letter of 
April 17 concerning the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claims. Excuses the former admissions of the 
Texan Grovemment and argues against the justice of the claims. <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will meet 
in November, and the subject will be presented to it again. Report House Committee 
on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 11-12. 

Burnet to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, June 16, 1839 (extract). Sends copy of a letter addressed by 
<ORGANIZATION>Burnet</ORGANIZATION> to the British consul at <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> relative to the <PERSON>Eliza Ru</PERSON>^eU claims, which 
have risen to double the amoimt originally demanded. Report House Committee 
on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 10-12. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, October 23, 1839. States the amount of the Eliza Rv^seU 
and Little <LOCATION>Penn</LOCATION> claims and refers to the promise by the Texan authorities to settle the 
first. The British Government would be justified in sending a ship of war to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> 
to enforce payment of the claims, but wishes to try one more application through 
<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 33-34; 
copy transmitted with <PERSON>Mcintosh</PERSON> to Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION>, November 12, 1839. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, October 23, 1839. Asks relief for certain British subjects, 
claiming lands in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Report House Conmdttee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. 
Cong., 35; Tel^raph and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> R^ter, October 18, 1843; The Morning Star (Hous- 
ton), October 14, 1843; copy transmitted with <PERSON>Mcintosh</PERSON> to Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION>, Novem- 
ber 12, 1839. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, October 30, 1839. Acknowledges receipt of both <PERSON>Palmer</PERSON>- 
ston's communications of the 23rd. Discusses the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claim and the land 
daims of certain British subjects. Report House Committee on Foreign Relations, 
4th Tex. Cong., 36-38; <ORGANIZATION>Journal</ORGANIZATION> and Advertiser (<LOCATION>San Augustine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>), June 11, 1840; 
Tel^raph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, October 18, 1843 (extract); The Morning Star, October 
14, 1843 (extract); copy transmitted with <PERSON>Mcintosh</PERSON> to Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION>, November 
12, 1839. 

aMatUated bj the pzlnter into <PERSON>Vogleraog</PERSON>. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



44 <ORGANIZATION>AMEEICAK HISTOBIOAL ASSOCIATION</ORGANIZATION>. 

<PERSON>Mcintosh</PERSON> to Secretary of <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION> [Burnet], November 12, 1839. <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> has left 
the business of the legation in <LOCATION>Mcintosh</LOCATION>'s hands. Incloses correspondence with 
British Government concerning claims against <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Existing Government too 
fearful of ofifending <PERSON>O'Oonnell</PERSON> and the Abolitionists to extend recognition to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 
Report House Gonmiittee on Foreign Relations, 4th Tex. Cong., 33-39. 

<PERSON>McGregor</PERSON> to President of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, December 26, 1839. Commander <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> has 
been ordered to support Commander <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> in his mission to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to recover 
certain ''British negroes'' supposed to be held in slavery in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 
5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 19. 

<PERSON>McGregor</PERSON> to President of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, December 26, 1839. Asks aid for Commander 
<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON>, of the British navy, in identifying and recovering certain negroes, sub- 
jects of <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, allied to be held in slavery in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>5th 
Tex.</LOCATION>, Cong., Appendix, 19-20. 

Burnet to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, January 29, 184Q. Professes ignorance of any negroes, British 
subjects, held in slavery in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, but promises assistance if such can be identified. 
<ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 22-23. 

<PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, February 14, 1840. Incloses Proclamation concerning 
negroes, British subjects all^^ed to be held in slavery in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th 
Tex. Cong., Appendix, 23-24. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Lipscomb</LOCATION>, February 25, 1840 (extract). Asks for commission to treat 
with <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> for recognition, and hopes for aid from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in securing a loan 
in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 284-285. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Lipscomb</LOCATION>, February 27, 1840. Demands delivery of negro ''John"» 
a British subject alleged to be held in slavery in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and incloses statement as to 
present ownership of said negro. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 20-21. 

<PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, March 31, 1840. Declares that question as to ownership 
of a certain n^;ro, if found to be a slave, must take usual course of law, but if proved to 
be a British subject will be delivered to proper authorities. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. 
Cong., Appendix, 24-25. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hamilton to Lipscomb</ORGANIZATION>, April 21, 1840. Acknowledges receipt of letter from Lips- 
comb, March 31, 1840. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 21-22. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hamilton to Lipscomb</ORGANIZATION>, April 21, 1840. Reports success in mission of identifying 
and recovering negroes, subjects of <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, alleged to be held in slavery in 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 22. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON>, June 3, 1840. Reports prospects for loan bright; reports 
chartering of vessels by <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> for attack on <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. House <PERSON>Jour</PERSON>- 
nal, <LOCATION>5th Tex</LOCATION>. Cong., Appendix, 285-286. 

<PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, June 6, 1840. Revokes instructions for purchase of arms, 
munitions, etc . , in <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> . <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex . Cong . , <PERSON>Appen</PERSON>- 
dix, 280-281. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, October 18, 1840. &lt;&gt; <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> is ready to enter into a com- 
mercial treaty with <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and to recognize her on condition that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> shall assist 
in suppressing the African slave trade. Incloses draft of a convention. Telegraph 
and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, January 12, 1842; copy inclosed with <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON>, 
January 4, 1841. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>, October 20, 1840. Acknowledges receipt of <LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION>'s 
letter of October 18, 1840, and the draft of a convention. With some slight changes, 
he is ready to sign it. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, January 12, 1842; copy inclosed 
with <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON>, January 4, 1841. 

<LOCATION>Palmerston</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, November 5, 1840. The signing of the treaty will have to 
be postponed a week. <ORGANIZATION>Colorado Gazette</ORGANIZATION> and Advertiser (<LOCATION>Matagorda</LOCATION>), January 23, 
1841; <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 382-383. 

a A few llnei at the beginning of the letter were omitted In printing It. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



CAI/ENDAB OF PBIKTED GOBBESPONDENCE. 45 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lamar</PERSON>, November 6, 1840. The preliminary articles of a treaty of 
recognition, amity, and commerce have been agreed upon. Incloses a copy of Pal- 
merston's note of November 6, 1840. <ORGANIZATION>Colorado Gazette</ORGANIZATION> and Advertiser, January 23, 
1841; <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 381-382. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 6, 1840 (extract). Has procured the recognition 
of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 156. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 8, 1842. The ratifications of the treaty have not yet been 
exchanged. The sympathies of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> are for <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and against <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 182-184. 

Teulon to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 25, 1842. Is still in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and without money. Has not 
faith in the ministry; it favors <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspond- 
ence, 189-190. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, July 10, 1842 (extract). Texan bonds in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. Incloses note 
from <PERSON>G. Shaw</PERSON> to Thos. <ORGANIZATION>Wilson A Co</ORGANIZATION>. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, February 22, 
1843. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, September 30, 1842. Uigee the claims of certain British subjects 
to lands in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, April 3, 1844. The Morning Star, 
April 2, 1844. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, December 24, 1842 (extract). The claims of the British subjects 
for lands in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>' will be presented to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, 
April 3, 1844; the Morning Star, April 2, 1844. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, January 31, 1843. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> is to make representations to the govern- 
ments of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> relative to the predatory warfare carried on by 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. Tel^;raph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, June 21, 1843. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, February 4, 1843. Presents the claims of <LOCATION>Beales</LOCATION> and others to lands 
in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. The Morning Star, April 2, 1844; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, April 3, 
1844. 

<PERSON>Jonee</PERSON> to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, February 16, 1843 . Has received his communications of January 17, 
1843, and February 4, 1843. Desires a personal interview with <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>. The Morning 
Star, April 9, 1844; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, April 10, 1844. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, June 10, 1843. The relations of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. The Red- 
Lander, April 20, 1844; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, November 13, 1844 (extract). 
Duplicate sent to <PERSON>Van Zandt</PERSON>. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, July 7, 1843. Is without authority to appoint a consul at <ORGANIZATION>Corpus 
Christi</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 226-227. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION>, August 1, 1843. The persons working in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> for the aboli- 
tion of slavery in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> are not recognized by the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> government. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Reg- 
ister, <ORGANIZATION>LXVI</ORGANIZATION>, 97; copy in <LOCATION>Smith</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, September 20, 1843. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, August 2, 1843. The abolition of slavery is the avowed purpose of 
the English Government. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 236-237. 
<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, August 17, 1843. The claims for the <PERSON>Eliza RtMell</PERSON> should be adjusted. 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 246-247. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, August 17, 1843 (extract). Hopes the President will make a repre- 
sentation to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> relative to the land claims of certain British subjects. The 
Morning Star, April 9, 1844; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, April 10, 1844. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, August 17, 1843. Urges settlement of <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON> claims. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 24^247. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, August 28, 1843. Believes General <PERSON>Houston</PERSON> will accede to the 
proposition of <LOCATION>Santa Anna</LOCATION> relative to the exchange of prisoners. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda 
and Official Correspondence, 248. 

<PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, September 4, 1843. Thanks him for his communication of 
August 20; 1843. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>^ Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 249 » 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



46 AMERICAN HISTOBICAIi ASSOCIATION. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, September 11, 1843. Glad that he has been able to settle the claim 
for the <PERSON>Eliza Rtissellj</PERSON> Relations with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official 
Correspondence, 250-253. 

<ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, September 11, 1843. Acknowledges <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>'s note of August 1. 
Her Majesty's Government has no intention of interfering in the internal affairs of 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, but wishes to see slavery abolished throu^out the world and is not surprised 
that private individuals should do their best to attain an object so desirable. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' 
Roister, <ORGANIZATION>LXVI</ORGANIZATION>, 97; copy in <LOCATION>Smith</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, September 20, 1843. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, September 14, 1843. Thanks him for his prompt attention to the 
case of the <PERSON>Eliza Russell</PERSON>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 256. 

Green to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, November 6, 1843. Requests copies of certain letters. Green^ 
Texan Expedition against <PERSON>Mier</PERSON>, 456; Tel^[raph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, December 13, 
1843; The Morning Star, December 12, 1843. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to Green, November 7, 1843. Declines his request for copies of certain letters. 
Green, Expedition against <PERSON>Mier</PERSON>, 456; Telegraph and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> R^^ister, December 13, 
1843; The Morning Star, December 12, 1843. 

Green to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, November 7, 1843. States reasons for applying for copies of certain 
letters on November 6, 1843. Green, Expedition against <PERSON>Mier</PERSON>, 456-457; <ORGANIZATION>Telegraph</ORGANIZATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, December 13, 1843; The Morning Star, December 12, 1843. 

<PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 9, 1843. Pringles project for a colony in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 269. 

<ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Pakenham</LOCATION>, December 26, 1843. <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> desires to see Texan 
Independence established, but with no occult designs. She wishes to see slavery 
abolished in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, but will not interfere unduly or improperly. <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Docs., 28th 
Cong., Ist Sess., V (Serial No. 435), <PERSON>Doc</PERSON>. 341, pp. 48-49; <PERSON>Nilee</PERSON>' Register, <ORGANIZATION>LXVI</ORGANIZATION>, 171; 
copy inclosed with <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, February 10, 1844. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, January 8, 1844. Has hesLrd that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> has settled her difficulties 
with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>; hopes for news of the release of the Texan prisoners. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda 
and Official Correspondence, 301. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, February 10, 1844. Sends a copy of a despatch from <LOCATION>Pakenham</LOCATION>. 
Is persuaded that annexation is entirely out of the question. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and 
Official Correspondence, 307-308. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, March 18, 1844. Incloses a copy of the proposed armistice between 
^exas and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, which can not be accepted. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official 
Correspondence, 327, 328. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, March 22, 1844. The British Government is engaged in an effort to 
procure the recognition of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. Asks for explanations concerning the 
contemplated move for annexation. Green, Expedition against <PERSON>Mier</PERSON>, 483; <PERSON>Nilee</PERSON>' 
Register, LXVIII, 35; The Red-Lander, June 15, 1844. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, March 22, 1844. Thanks him for his letter of February 16, 1844. 
Believes that annexation will be defeated in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 329-331. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, March 25, 1844. Gives the explanations requested by <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> in his 
note of March 22, 1844. The Red-Lander, June 15, 1844. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 3, 1844. Believes the time very favorable for the mediation 
of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Register, <ORGANIZATION>LXVI</ORGANIZATION>, 280; The Red-Lander, June 15, 
1844; The Morning Star, June 8, 1844; Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Roister</ORGANIZATION>, June 12, 1844. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 2, 1844 (extract). <PERSON>Lord Aberdeen</PERSON> remarked that he would 
say nothing more about slavery. The Red-Lander, August 31, 1844. 

<PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 3, 1844. Received <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>'s letters of May 2 and 19, 1844. 
Can not come to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 
357-359. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, imdated (extract). Has informed British Government of <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>'s 
determination to sustain the independence of the Republic, and supposes that Hender- 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



CAIiENDAB OF PBINTED CORRESPONDENCE. 47 

son's mission to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is to explain this position. The Morning Star, 
June 27, 1844. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, September 30, 1844 (extract). The subject of abolition can not 
and will not be entertained by the Government of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. The Red-Lander, August 
31, 1844. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, December 24, 1844. Just arrived from <LOCATION>Liverpool</LOCATION>. Tells of inter- 
views with <PERSON>Guizot</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 
411-412. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>, January 8, 1845. Asks for settlement of <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION> claims, and 
incloses declaration of <PERSON>Thomas Hibbert</PERSON>, September 16, 1844, in support of said claim. 
<ORGANIZATION>Senate Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 9th Tex. Cong., extra sess., 62-64. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, January 14, 1845. General <PERSON>Green</PERSON> is singing another veme to the 
tune of British influence. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 413-414. 

<PERSON>Terrell</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, January 21, 1845. Has been in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> nine days. Tells of an 
interview with <ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 415-417. 

<PERSON>Terrell</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, February 2, 1845 (extract). Since his last despatch he has had 
two interviews with <ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION>. Was assured that <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> had no desire to acquire 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 419-420. 

<PERSON>Terrell</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, February 13, 1845. Has arrived at <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>; before 
leaving he had a conversation with <ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION> who was rather cool, having heard that 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> favored annexation. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 422-431. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON>, February 22, 1845. Denies validity of <LOCATION>Little Penn</LOCATION> claim on grounds 
that goods really belonged to Mexicans. <ORGANIZATION>Senate Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 9th Tex. Cong., extra sess., 
64-67. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <ORGANIZATION>Aberdeen</ORGANIZATION>, March 31, 1845. It has been thought advisable to have <PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> 
go to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 475-476. . 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 3, 1845. The new government in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> adheree to the 
favorable disposition expressed by <PERSON>Santa Anna</PERSON>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official 
Correspondence, 441. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 5, 1845. Will leave on the Eurydice. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and 
Official Correspondence, 443. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 9, 1845. Fears that when it is known that he has been sent 
to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> public opinion will become inflamed beyond control. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda 
and Official Correspondence, 446-449. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 14, 1845. Will proceed at once to <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> and embark for 
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> where he will use every exertion to accomplish his mission. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memo- 
randa and Official Correspondence, 451. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 21, 1845. The Government of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> has demanded of Con- 
gress the authority to treat with <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspond- 
ence, 452-453. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, May 1, 1845. Arrived at <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>; leaves at once for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. His 
journey has caused much speculation in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and 
Official Correspondence, 456-457. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 12, 1845. The excitement in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> may drive the 
Mexicans out of the humor of complying with the preliminaries of the treaty. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 468-469. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 13, 1845. Should the present storm blow over, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> can rely 
on the friendship of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Implores Jones</PERSON> to preserve <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda 
and Official Correspondence, 470-471. 

EUiot to <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>, June 13, 1845. Takes formal leave upon departing from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Senate Joiunal</ORGANIZATION>, 9th Tex. Cong., extra sess., 67-68. 

<PERSON>Allen</PERSON> to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, June 26, 1845. There is no doubt that annexation will be accom- 
plished; recalls <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>. The Morning Star, August 16, 1845; Telegraph and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> 
B^;ister, Au^;u8t 20, 184^. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



48 <ORGANIZATION>AMERICAN HISTORICAIi ASSOCIATION</ORGANIZATION>. 

<PERSON>Terrell</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, July 25, 1845 (extract). Has just arrived from <LOCATION>Liverpool</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 481. 

<PERSON>Elliot</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, January 4, 1846. Sends a copy of a despatch from <LOCATION>Lord Aberdeen</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 508. 

COEBBSPONDBNCE WTTH PRANCE. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, October 6, 1838. Had an interview with Count Mol^ relative 
to recognition. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 133-135. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, October 28, 1838. Believes <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will be recognized by <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> 
before March. He is not much concerned about a commercial arrangement. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 135-137. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 12, 1838 (extract). The withdrawal of the annexa- 
tion proposition has removed the one obstacle to the recognition of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. His proposition for a commercial arrangement will be accepted by the 
French King. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 137-138. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, December 5, 1838 (extract). Thinks <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> should not allow 
vessels manned by free n^;roe8 to enter her ports. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official 
Correspondence, 138-139. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, December 28, 1838. Nothing of importance has transpired 
since his last. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 144-145. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, June 20, 1839. The French King is anxious to recognize <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> 
provided <PERSON>Saligny</PERSON>'s report is favorable. <PERSON>Pontois</PERSON> thinks that the question of slavery is 
influencing <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> to delay recognition. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Cor- 
respondence, 146-147. 

Soult to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, September 12, 1839. The <LOCATION>Republic of France</LOCATION> will facilitate the 
n^otiation of the loan. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, February 16, 1842. 

<PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, September 27, 1839 (extract). Has completed the n^otiation 
for the loan. Will leave for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> in a few days. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official 
Correspondence, 1,47-148. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, March 24, 1840. Tells of his part in bringing about recognition by 
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 153-155. 

Guizot to <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, March 31, 1841. Received his letter in which he recalls the 
promise of <PERSON>Marshall Soult</PERSON>. A guaranty of such a nature would have to be submitted 
to the Chambers. Doubts its passage. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, February 16, 
1842. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Guizot</LOCATION>, April 21, 1841. Regrets that the Government has withdrawn 
its guaranty of the loan. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, February 16, 1842. 

<LOCATION>Saligny</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 21, 1841 (extract). His Government has vindicated 
him of the charges against him and he is preparing to return to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memo- 
randa and Official Correspondence, 173-174. 

<LOCATION>Saligny</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, December 6, 1841 (extract). Thinks the views of his Government 
relative to the charges against him are as conciliatory as those of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memo- 
randa and Official Correspondence, 174-177. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, March 2, 1842. Thinks that the Saligny affair should be kept 
open no longer. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 177. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, January 31, 1843. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> is to make representations to the Crovem- 
ments of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> relative to the predatory warfare carried on by 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. Telegraph and <ORGANIZATION>Texas Register</ORGANIZATION>, June 21, 1843. 

<PERSON>Jones</PERSON> to <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jime</PERSON> 10, 1843. See Calendar of Correspondence with <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>. 

<ORGANIZATION>Hughes</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 24, 1843 (extract). Claims credit for securing recogni- 
tion of Texan independence by <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in 1839. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Cor- 
respondence, 271-273. 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



CALENDAB OF PRINTED COBBBSPONDENCE. 49 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, January 29, 1844. Believes the best feelings are entertained for 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> both at <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and 0£icial Oonre^pondence, 
304-305. 

Guizot to <LOCATION>Saligny</LOCATION>, August 1, 1844. <LOCATION>Saligny</LOCATION> is to discourage annexation as much as 
possible. <PERSON>Niles</PERSON>' Roister, <ORGANIZATION>LXIX</ORGANIZATION>, 403. 

<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 14, 1844. Glad to hear ol his election as President. 
<PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Copespondence, 399-401. 

<PERSON>Terrell</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 22, 1844 (extract). <PERSON>Saligny</PERSON> has received despatches 
Erom his Government on the subject of annexatiim. <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> will give the guaranty 
spoken of by Doctor <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> provided <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> will suspend annexation operations. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Corre^)ondence, 404-405. 

<LOCATION>Saligny</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 3, 1845 (extract). Has received cheering news from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. 
Leaves for <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> soon. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 443- 
444. 

<LOCATION>Saligny</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, May, 1845. The Deputies of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> have declared in favor of 
Texan independence by a vote of 41-43. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspond- 
ence, 463-464. 

<PERSON>DeCyprey</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, May 20, 1845. See Calendar of Correspondence with the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in Part <PERSON>I. 

Jones</PERSON> to DeCyprey, June 6, 1845. See Calendar of Correspondence with the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> in Part 1. 

CORBBSPONDBNCB WITH <LOCATION>SPAIN</LOCATION>. 

<PERSON>Fisher</PERSON> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, May 3, 1842. Gives news of movement of Spanish fleet in the 
<LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION>, and suggests that n^otiations be opened with <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> for a treaty of 
commerce in order that she may not force the blockade. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and 
Official Correspondence, 195-196. 

CORBBSPONDBNCB WITH BBLOIUM. 

<PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON> to <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Burnley</ORGANIZATION>, April 18, 1840. <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> is authorized to 
negotiate a treaty of amity and commerce with <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>. Relations between <LOCATION>Great 
Britain</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, and status of affairs between <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 277-280. 

CORBBSPONDBNCB WITH THB NBTHBRLAJ^DS. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON>, June 6, 1840. Asks for power to treat with <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION> for the recognition of independence, and for conunercial treaties. <ORGANIZATION>House 
Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 286. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <PERSON>Lipscomb</PERSON>, July 28, 1840. Reports progress of n^otiations with the 
<LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> for recognition preparatory to securing a loan, and discusses prospects 
for securing a loan in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., 
Appendix, 287-291. 

<PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Lipscomb</LOCATION>, September 1, 1840. Reports on course of negotiations with 
the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> for recognition, and discusses prospects for securing a loan in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>House Journal</ORGANIZATION>, 5th Tex. Cong., Appendix, 292-293. 

CORRBSPONDBNCE WITH THB HAN8E TOWNS. 

<LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, February 4, 1843. Has received information relative to the 
government of the Hanse Towns. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 
207-209. 

<LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, April 22, 1844. Sends greetings. For official information 
refers to despatches of the same date. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, Memoranda and Official Correspond- 
ence, 347-348. 

39728**— VOL 2, pt 1—11 4 



Digitized by 



<ORGANIZATION>Google</ORGANIZATION> 



50 <ORGANIZATION>AMEBICAN HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION</ORGANIZATION>. 

<LOCATION>Daingerfield</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, November 8, 1844. Congratulates <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> on hb election to 
the Presidency. Has been counteracting Mexican influence in <LOCATION>Hamburg</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, 
Memoranda and Official Correspondence, 394-396. 

COBRE8PONDBNCB WITH THE PAPAL STATES. 
